McKenzie is one of the most influential
companies in the world. And if you've
barely heard the name, that's exactly
what they want. They've worked for 90 of
the 100 biggest companies on Earth.
Boeing, Coca-Cola, Microsoft, Google,
the top banks, big oil, big tobacco,
along with the White House, the
Pentagon, the NSA, Saudi Arabia, China,
Russia, South Africa, and dozens of
other governments. And as you'll see in
this story, the outcomes can hardly be
said to benefit your life.
>> There's no point not to hire McKenzie if
you can afford it because it's a SWAT
team of analysts that is at your beck
and [music] call. It's basically a firm
that will come into the office and say,
"What do you want us to [music] do?"
>> Our purpose is to create positive
enduring change in the world. The work
of McKenzie colleagues matters to
clients, their customers, and society.
We think we have the best people. That's
the pitch in a nutshell. So, let's walk
through the McKenzie Hall of Fame to see
how it translates. Start with Kmart,
Enron, and General Motors. All once too
big to fail, all clients, and then all
bankrupt. Enron was later exposed in
some of the worst accounting fraud in
history. 20,000 people lost their jobs
and pensions. The CEO who went to prison
was a McKenzie [music] partner. Then
there's Disney. A consultant asked why
mechanics checked the roller coaster's
lap bars every day when the record
showed they'd never failed. Disney
switched to what a lawsuit called a
runtofailure approach. A will then came
off Big Thunder Mountain and killed a
22-year-old. In 2016, they built loyalty
schemes for Marro, including an app that
handed out novelty prizes for smoking
more. You could even win a drone if you
smoked enough. At AT&T, they told them
mobile phones were niche and no one
would buy them. Need I say any more than
that? At Swiss Air, they told them to
buy up stakes in rival airlines. Within
four years, they were grounded on the
tarmac. And littered throughout every
job, you have their house specialtity,
mass layoffs, costing Americans an
estimated 5 million jobs. But we've not
yet reached to the jewel of their crown.
The year is 2004, and the goal at the
farmer giant Pery was simple. Increase
drug sales and make as much cash as
humanly possible. The product is
Oxycontton, an opioid with a well-known
link to addiction. And there are
millions of Americans who could be
buying more of it. So, first they needed
to identify the doctors prescribing the
most pills. Then create a marketing
campaign and target those doctors. Then
increase the dosage to maximize
addiction revenue. And then there's the
problem of teenagers overdosing and
their mothers talking about it to the
press. We need a better way to counter
this. And let's convince the FDA that
Oxycontton is safe for kids.
>> We sell hope in a bottle. This is an
advertising campaign you came [music] up
with. We sell hope in a bottle. That's
for opioids.
Hope in a bottle. You help Purdue Pharma
market them to children. These are the
results. [snorts] It's actually
difficult to overstate how devastating
Peru's actions were for America. Oxy
then stuck a rocket up heroin and
fentinyl addiction rates. When the pills
were reformulated to be harder to crush,
millions of people were already
dependent. So the supply moved to heroin
than fentinyl. And it all began with
interns and suits and a PowerPoint
presentation. Exactly how you imagine
the benality of evil.
>> It's exactly that profit at all costs.
McKenzie Consultants were about the
business of advising their clients on
how to make as much money as possible
from this deadly epidemic. It shows a
callousness that really is beyond the
pale and it's why McKenzie needs to be
held accountable.
>> But this is actually the one that got
away from McKenzie. They were forced to
pay $650 million for their involvement
in the entire crisis. A senior partner,
Martin Elling, emailed himself a to-do
list, including deleting the old Purdue
files from his laptop. He was the only
one convicted for the entire ordeal. No
lessons were learned as just a couple of
years later, Valiian suffered a
remarkably similar fate, hiking drug
prices under Mckenzie's advice and
ruining thousands of rare disease
sufferers lives. Some drugs went from a
few hundred to over $20,000. There was a
Senate hearing and the company
collapsed. Valiant was too aggressive
and I as its leader was also too
aggressive.
>> You'd surely think a company like
McKenzie has no hope of surviving any of
this. If you did even a tiny fraction of
any of these mistakes, you'd be in
prison forever. But they still turn over
$16 billion every year. Yet what reads
like a catalog of tragic errors to any
sane individual reads like an amazing CV
to their prospective clients because the
skills honed in the soulless corporate
world were about to prove priceless for
governments and their heenous policies.
And so what better match for McKenzie
than Saudi Arabia. You see the Saudis
have just scaled back their embarrassing
dystopia of neon. Work on the line has
been halted until after 2030. The CEO is
gone after $8 billion down the drain.
But now you might not be surprised to
know that McKenzie made a ton of money
out of it first and probably helped a
few others do the same along the way.
McKenzie might build slideshows instead
of buildings, but they designed the
entire scope of the project. For it,
their fee was over $130 million a year.
But there's something about this story
that's almost too absurd to be true. You
see, the government hired McKenzie to
audit McKenzie's own plans, and they
admitted they were completely
makebelieve. But don't mistake that as
an unlikely turn for their honesty. More
problems mean more expenditure, which is
why the project is now expected to take
until 2080 and will cost a light sum of
$8.8 trillion. That's more than 25 times
the entire Saudi government budget and
more than the GDP of every country on
Earth except America and China. All that
death of the people that used to live
there, the destruction and the burnt
cash for a few foundations that will get
covered by the sand and then eventually
forgotten. McKenzie had actually carried
out hundreds of projects for Saudi
Arabia, including the country's
surveillance operations. They were also
tasked with identifying the most
prominent Saudi dissident on social
media. The list of targets included a
close associate of Jamal Kosigible, the
dissident who was eventually
assassinated. The United Nations has
just issued its report on the murder of
Jamal Hashajji. The Saudi journalist was
killed in the Saudi consulate in
Istanbul in October last year. The CIA
and some Western countries believe Crown
Prince Muhammad bin Salman, Saudi
Arabia's de facto ruler, ordered the
killing. Saudi officials have always
denied this. Others involved were
arrested or hounded by law enforcement
and this is still just scratching the
surface of their work across the globe.
In China, their operation spanned nearly
three decades. McKenzie co-founded the
Urban China Initiative which researched
smart cities and brought China's
urbanization to the next level. A
McKenzie partner helped them work out
how China could dominate tech with
robotics, AI, and data. Over in Russia,
they were contracted with the
state-owned arms company Rosstec, as
well as Kremlin linked banks. Rosstec
supplies Putin's military and is run by
a former KGB officer who served
alongside him. And all that while the US
military was paying them over $480
million on the F-35 fighter program,
while also on American naval bases and
on Air Force missile command. So, they
helped design Russia and China strategy
and then got paid to counter it. Why did
you advise on 22 of the 100 biggest
Chinese state-owned enterprises? [music]
>> That number I don't believe is accurate,
Senator.
>> It doesn't have anything to do with
money, does it?
>> I don't believe that number is accurate.
Senator,
>> how much money do you make off the
United States government?
>> I don't know the size of our work with
the US government. Senator,
>> in 2021, you made more than $850 million
in consulting work for the federal
government with the Department of
Defense as your top client. You can't
forget their infamous involvement in
South Africa where they got caught up in
allegations surrounding the president
essentially corrupting the entire
country. They got hold of confidential
information and used it as leverage to
make millions of dollars. When exposed,
they went and denied it all. We've
examined all the evidence we could find
about our work for ESCOM. 9 million
emails, hundreds of thousands of
documents, including telephone logs,
personal emails, financial records, and
we conducted over 80 interviews.
The facts are we found no evidence our
firm engaged in corrupt activity. Let me
repeat this as it is important. We found
no evidence that our firm engaged in
corrupt activity. [music]
But just 4 years later, the partner at
the center of it pleaded guilty to
bribery. They finally admitted
responsibility, repaid all fees with
interest, and handed over another 62
million to South Africa. They're not
deterred by these national controversies
as shown in 2015 when Iran's economy was
labeled as a trillion dollar growth
opportunity. That opportunity is
currently a war zone and we all know how
profitable that is for the right people.
The thing you realize with McKenzie is
their work always comes across as a pure
screw-up where no one benefits. But
someone somewhere is making generational
wealth and the consequences are rarely
as accidental as they appear. They serve
a lot of clients with really harmful
effects. They know exactly what the
repercussions are going to be and then
they say, "We're going to do it anyway."
[music] And that tells you all you need
to know about the firm. Peel back the
layers and you eventually find the
insane power of an innermost circle
they've built over almost 100 years
because behind the army of suits is an
influence unlike any company on the
planet. [music] Ta how one of the
McKenzie consultants on their Pentagon
projects was Pete Puda Judge who right
now is one of the front runners to be
the next Democratic candidate for
president. He was 25 at the time and his
client list included the Department of
Defense, the US Postal Service and a
health insurer called Blue Cross Blue
Shield of Michigan. 2 years after he
worked on finding savings there, Blue
Cross cut a thousand jobs and asked the
state for permission to raise individual
premiums by 55%.
That was 418,000
people, about half of them pensioners.
Now he turns up on podcasts like an
enlightened man.
>> Not whether they exist, it's having too
much power. It's it's being able to turn
economic power into political power and
[music] then using that power to get
even more wealth. whole lot of people
who didn't just lose their jobs, never
recovered their sense of identity.
>> But the McKenzie alumni runs much deeper
than this. Media CEOs and executives
from the BBC, CNBC, Disney, and ITV,
healthcare leaders like FISA's Amir
Malik, who ran McKenzie's entire US
operation for 25 years, which makes
sense because McKenzie was all over the
pandemic response, taking hundreds of
thousands of pounds of taxpayer money in
the UK, too. eight banking CEOs and
executives, including the woman running
City Group right now, plus Morgan
Stanley, HSBC, UBS, Credit Seuss, and
the chief operating officer of the Bank
of England, a prince of the Dutch royal
family, Germany's richest woman, and the
late Queen's assistant private
secretary, CEOs and executives from BMW,
Rolls-Royce, Door Dash, Uber, the Ford
Foundation, Lego, FIFA, Ticket Master,
Microsoft, Yahoo, Meta, Talk, Vodafone,
and Open AI. the co-founder of
match.com, the monopoly that owns Tinder
Hinge, and over 40 other dating apps,
the man who ran Boeing for a decade, who
optimized the company for profit and
helped push the 737 Max. Two crashes in
5 months, and 346 people dead. Seven
Google executives, including the CEO,
Sundai Pachchai, Peter Atier, who we've
covered before due to his connections to
Epstein and his friendship with Joe
Rogan, a handful of Hollywood
screenwriters, even the Clinton's own
daughter, Chelsea Clinton, and finally
at least 47 prominent politicians, the
sitting prime minister of Greece, a
former British foreign secretary, a
former US national security adviser, the
EU's climate commissioner, and a sitting
US senator. It's really a long, endless,
and stunning list, but it's super dark
now that you know the dark way ethics
are twisted inside the organization
itself and the impact and destruction
it's done to our society. And for all
the scary things about them and what
they do, that is probably the scariest
thing about McKenzie. Because they
aren't only making highstakes decisions
that judge lives in a mathematical
equation, but they're also cooking up
the decision makers of our world within
the belly of their corporate machine. In
fact, there was a Channel 4 UK
documentary in 1999 where they went
behind the scenes in McKenzie's
recruitment stage. At one point, they
started joking around about laying
workers off in a training exercise. Even
in this created section of McKenzie, it
looks so out of touch.
>> We got a very simple strategy. Just
hit the road, Jack, and don't come back.
That's not our communication strategy.
>> I think the part that I learned the most
about was actually roleplaying the
client and seeing looking back at us and
how sometimes we can be really
offensive. That was quite insightful to
just always force yourself to take their
view of the world. The documentary also
included a bizarre internal promo video
of some kind.
>> We've never been more successful than we
are today. The reason, we know our
strengths and our limits. Our main
problem is managing our expectations. We
live with the constant fear that failure
is only one study away. We are insecure
overachievers.
But fear of failure can be a strength if
it helps keep us sharp. The
Machavevelian psychology on display here
is now embedded in powerful institutions
that affect every aspect of your life.
It's the global offer you get at work.
It's the job you work faithfully for
years and then are cut off like you're
nothing. It's the billions sucked out of
the economy by those with access. It's
the great wealth transfer. It's the
difficult decisions governments make
that prop up their allies while grinding
society into dust. It's the reason our
culture is so perverted. It's the prices
that magically rise because they tell us
we're in a recession. But the
shareholder dividends grow and grow and
grow. And most of all, it's the reason
for the surveillance state we now all
live in. But it does seem deep within
the McKenzie consciousness that they do
know they are the lowest of the low.
They represent and strengthen
surveillance states, disgraced farmer
companies, authoritarian governments,
and dystopian corporations. They are the
opioid of the corporate world, and
they've got everyone hooked. yet somehow
are completely inevitable in a supply
and demand economy where necessity is
the mother of all invention because
people crave money and power and
McKenzie was invented to serve that
craving. That's why they are the best
team for carrying out the dirty work.
The dirty work you have to live in.